Finding Aid for Richard D. Mann papers, 1965-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard D. Mann papers 1965-1984
Mann, Richard D. (Richard Dewey), 1933-
5 linear inches (in 1 box)
88244 Aa 2
Professor of psychology at the University of Michigan, and an organizer of the teach-ins on the Vietnam War in Ann Arbor, Michigan, and elsewhere, 1965-1966. Autobiographical papers; files on the protest against the Vietnam War; and materials on Program for Educational and Social Change, an effort to open university courses to the local community.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Mann (donor no. 7487 )
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard D. Mann, University of Michigan psychology professor, played an important role in organizing the Ann Arbor and National teach-ins on the Vietnam War during the spring of 1965. He continued his activist attempts to make education timely and relevant by designing courses to examine the dynamics of student protest at Columbia and during the Black Action Movement at the University of Michigan. He also participated in efforts to open university courses to members of the local community through the short-lived Program for Educational and Social Change in 1972.
The Richard D. Mann papers are arranged in chronological order according to his teach-in activism and teaching activities. The materials include correspondence, notes of telephone conversations and meetings, leaflets, course material, research papers, conference pamphlets, and printed materials. The Vietnam War Protest materials contain interesting correspondence with McGeorge Bundy, national security advisor to President Johnson, and Mann's organizational notes. The Program for Educational and Social Change materials detail Mann's efforts to teach free courses on community activism and the response of the university administration to his efforts.
Subjects:
Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Contributors:
Bundy, McGeorge.
- Teaching and teach-in activities
  - Autobiographic Musings, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Vietnam War Protest, 1965-1966
    - Ann Arbor Teach-in, March-April 1965 (Box 1)
    - National Teach-in, March-June 1965
      - Correspondence with McGeorge Bundy, March-April 1965 (Box 1)
      - Mann's notes, April-May 1965 (Box 1)
      - Program and General Correspondence, April-June 1965 (Box 1)
    - International Conference, September 1965-January 1966 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, April-May 1965 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Sociology/Psychology 988, 1968-1970
    - Columbia, 1968-1969
      - Bureau of Applied Social Research Papers, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - Handouts to Class, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Magazine Articles and Clippings, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Other Student Revolts, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Black Action Movement (BAM), 1970
      - Chronology, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Clippings and Press Releases, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Letters to Michigan Daily, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Identity of the Group Research, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Program for Educational and Social Change (PESC), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Peace Studies, 1984 (Box 1)